<stage rend="italic">Enter Duke, Viola, Curio, and others.</stage>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>Giue me some Misick; Now good morow frends.</l>
<l>Now good <hi rend="italic">Cesario</hi>, but that peece of song,</l>
<l>That old and Anticke song we heard last night;</l>
<l>Me thought it did releeue my passion much,</l>
<l>More then light ayres, and recollected termes</l>
<l>Of these most briske and giddy-paced times.</l>
<l>Come, but one verse.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Cur. </speaker><p>He is not heere (so please your Lordshippe) that should sing it?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><p>Who was it?</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Cur. </speaker><p><hi rend="italic">Feste</hi> the Iester my Lord, a foole that the Ladie <hi rend="italic">Oliuiaes</hi> Father tooke much delight in. He is about the house.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>Seeke him out, and play the tune the while.</l>
<stage rend="italic">Musicke playes</stage>
<l>Come hither Boy, if euer thou shalt loue</l>
<l>In the sweete pangs of it, remember me:</l>
<l>For such as I am, all true Louers are,</l>
<l>Vnstaid and skittith in all motions else,</l>
<l>Saue in the constant image of the creature</l>
<l>That is belou'd. How dost thou like this tune?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>It giues a verie eccho to the seate</l>
<l>Where loue is thron'd.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>Thou dost speake masterly,</l>
<l>My life vpon't, yong thou thou art, thine eye</l>
<l>Hath staid vpon some favour that it loues:</l>
<l>Hath it not boy?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>A little, by your favour.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>What kinde of woman ist?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>Of your complection.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>She is not worth thee then. What yeeres ifaith?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>About your yeeres my Lord.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>Too old by heauen: Let still the woman take</l>
<l>An elder then her selfe, so weares she to him;</l>
<l>So swayes she leuell in her husbands heart:</l>
<l>For boy, howeuer we do praise our selues,</l>
<l>Our fancies are more giddie and vnfirme,</l>
<l>More longing, wauering, sooner lost and worne,</l>
<l>Then womens are.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>I think it well my Lord.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>Then let thy Loue be yonger then thy selfe,</l>
<l>Or thy affection cannot hold the bent:</l>
<l>For women are as Roses, whose faire flowre</l>
<l>Being once displaid, oth fall that verie howre.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>An so they are: alas, that they are so:</l>
<l>To die, euen when they to perfection grow.</l></sp>
<stage rend="italic">Enter Curio &amp; Clowne</stage>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>O fellow come, the song we had last night:</l>
<l>Marke it Cesario, it is old and plaine;</l>
<l>The Spinsters and the Knitter in the Sun,</l>
<l>And the free maides that weaue their thred with bones,</l>
<l>Do vse to chaunt it: it is silly sooth,</l>
<l>And dallies with the innocence of loue,</l>
<l>Like the old age.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Clo. </speaker><l>Are you ready Sir?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>I prethee sing.</l></sp>
<stage rend="italic">Musicke.</stage>
<head rend="italic">The Song.</head>
<lg><l rend="italic">Come away, come away death,</l>
<l rend="italic">And in sad cypresse let me be laide.</l>
<l rend="italic">Fye away, fie away breath,</l>
<l rend="italic">I am slaine by a faire cruell maide:<lb/>
My shrowd of white stuck all with Ew, O prepare it.<lb/>
My part of death no one so true did share it.</l></lg>
<lg><l rend="italic">Not a flower, not a flower sweete</l>
<l rend="italic">On my blacke coffin, let there be strewne:</l>
<l rend="italic">Not a friend, not a friend greet</l>
<l rend="italic">My poore corpes, where my bones shall be threwne:<lb/>
A thousand thousand sighes to saue, lay me &ocirc; where<lb/>
Sad true louer neuer find my graue, to weepe there.</l></lg>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><p>There's for thy paines.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Clo. </speaker><p>No paines sir, I take pleasure in singing sir.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><p>He pay thy pleasure then.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Clo. </speaker><p>Truely sir, and pleasure will be paide one time, or another.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><p>Giue me now leaue, to leaue thee.</p></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Clo. </speaker><p>Now the melancholly God protect thee, and the Tailor make thy doublet of changeable Taffeta, for thy mind is very Opall. I would haue men of such constancie put to Sea, that their businesse might be euery thing, and their intent euerie where, for that's it, that alwayes makes a good voyage of nothing. Farewell.</p></sp>
<stage rend="italic">Exit</stage>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>Let all the rest giue place: Once more <hi rend="italic">Cesario,</hi></l>
<l>Get thee to yond soueraigne crueltie:</l>
<l>Tell her my loue, more noble then the world</l>
<l>Prizes not quantitie of dirtie lands,</l>
<l>The parts that fortune hath bestow'd vpon her:</l>
<l>Tell her I hold as giddily as Fortune:</l>
<l>But 'tis that miracle, as Queene of Iems</l>
<l>That nature prankes her in, attracts my soule.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>But if she cannot loue you sir.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>It cannot be so answer'd.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Viol. </speaker><l>Sooth but you must.</l>
<l>Say that some Lady, as perhappes there is,</l>
<l>Hath for your loue as great a pang of heart</l>
<l>As you haue for <hi rend="italic">Olivia</hi>: you cannot loue her:</l>
<l>You tel her so: Must she not then be answer'd?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>There is no womans sides</l>
<pb n="263"/>
<l>Can bide the beating of so strong a passion,</l>
<l>As loue doth giue my heart: no womans heart</l>
<l>So bigge, to hold so much, they lacke retention.</l>
<l>Alas, their loue may be call'd appetite,</l>
<l>No motion of the liuer, but by Pallat,</l>
<l>that suffer surfet, cloyment, and reuolt,</l>
<l>But mine is all as hungry as the Sea,</l>
<l>And can digest as much, make no compare</l>
<l>Between that loue a woman can beare me,</l>
<l>And that I owe <hi rend="italic">Olivia</hi>.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Viol. </speaker><l>I but I know.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>What doest thou knowe?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Viol. </speaker><l>Too well what loue wome to men may owe:</l>
<l>In faith they are as true of heart, as we.</l>
<l>My father had a daughter lou'd a man</l>
<l>As it might be perhaps, were I a woman</l>
<l>A should your lordship.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>And what's her history?</l></sp>
<sp><spekaer rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>A blanke my Lord: she never told her loue,</l>
<l>But let concealment like a worme i'th budde</l>
<l>Feede on her damaske cheeke: she pin'd in thought,</l>
<l>And with a greene and yellow melancholly,</l>
<l>She sate like Patience on a Monument,</l>
<l>Similing at greese. Was not this loue indeede?</l>
<l>We men may say more, sweare more, but indeed</l>
<l>Our shewes are more then will: for still we proue</l>
<l>Much in our vowes, but little in our loue.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>But di'de thy sister of her loue my boy?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Vio. </speaker><l>I am all the daughters of my Fathers house,</l>
<l>And all the brothers too: and yet I know not.</l>
<l>Sir, shall I to this lady?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker rend="italic">Du. </speaker><l>I that's the Theame,</l>
<l>To her in haste: giue her this Iewell: say,</l>
<l>My loue can giue no place, bide no denay.</l></sp>
<stage rend="italic">exeunt</stage>
